since the scientific age began we've
lived in a universe where the bottom
strata of reality is considered to be
something that's dead like dirt it's
like it's matter its objective its
external and there isn't any element of
it that lends any reality to phenomena
like meaning or purpose that's all being
relegated to the subjective and in some
ways to the illusory but it's by no
means self-evident that that set of
presuppositions is correct because we
lacked infinite knowledge and there's
many things about the structure of being
that we don't understand the main one
being consciousness we can't account for
it at all and we can't account for the
role it appears to play in the
transformation of potential into
actuality which is a role that's been
recognized by physicists for almost a
hundred years now
and which remains one of the biggest
unsolved mysteries in science there are
other ways of looking at what's real and
these other ways have some advantages
and one of the advantages they have is
that they protect us knowing these other
ways of operating within reality
defining reality protect us from certain
kinds of pathologies and modern people
are prone to a fair number of
pathologies that stem from the
assumptions of their of their of the
systems they use to define reality and
one of those pathologies is a kind of a
nihilistic hopelessness which is a
consequence of the recognition that in
the final analysis nothing really has
any meaning and because life is
difficult and that's a meaning that you
can't escape being forced to abandon
your belief in a positive or a
transcendent meaning can leave you weak
the times when you really can least
afford to be weak and there's more
important pathologies that it's opened
us up to - and those are pathologies of
belief and I think we saw the most
horrifying examples of that hopefully
the most horrifying example
the 20th century where people whose
belief systems were shattered at least
in part by the competition between
religious and scientific viewpoints
turned in large numbers to mass
movements that were in error in every
way a substitute a more rational in some
sense substitute for religious beliefs
that appeared no longer tenable and the
consequence of that was it was just
about annihilation because we came close
to annihilation twice once in the 60s
and once in the 80s and even without the
totality of annihilation we lost
hundreds of millions of people as a
consequence of pathological belief
systems in the 20th century
you